<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>tomp.io</title><link href="http://tomp.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://tomp.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://tomp.io/</id><updated>2014-12-20T12:39:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Issues in Open Research Data: Health</title><link href="http://tomp.io/issues-in-open-research-data.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-12-20T12:39:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Tom Pollard</name></author><id>tag:tomp.io,2014-12-20:issues-in-open-research-data.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;meta name="twitter:card" content="photo" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:site" content="@tompollard" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:title" content="Issues in Open Research Data" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:description" content="Culture is largely the barrier that restricts flow of research data" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:image" content="http://tomp.io/images/issues_open_research_data_1.png" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:url" content="http://tomp.io/issues-in-open-research-data" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The following text is reproduced from Samuel Moore's book on Issues in Open Research Data:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Issues in Open Research Data Header" src="images/issues_open_research_data_1.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we pass through life in the digital era we leave a health trajectory in our wake. Phones, shopping habits, and visits to the doctor create a trace of data that can be used to not only assess our past and present wellbeing, but also forecast the future. To some, this is an unparalleled opportunity to improve health care, whereas to others it is an emerging threat to civil liberty. Most of us camp somewhere between the two poles: we see the rewards and we acknowledge the concerns. The question is how we move past this point, when business models and legal frameworks, built for a pre-internet world, struggle to keep up with the pace of change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The movement to give us open access to research articles began roughly fifteen years ago. Before the dust has settled, there is now a strong push from researchers, funders, and publishers to open the data that underpins those articles. The suggestion to share research data is hardly new, but technology now exists to enable sharing with relative ease. Culture is largely the barrier that restricts flow of research data, and for data sharing to be adopted there are challenges to overcome around privacy, competition, and incentives to share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continued in: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pollard, T. and Celi, L. A. 2014. Open Data in Health Care. In: Moore, S. A. (ed.) Issues in Open Research Data. Pp. 129–140. London: ­Ubiquity Press. DOI: &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5334/ban.h"&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.5334/ban.h&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Issues in Open Research Data. Edited by Samuel Moore" src="images/issues_open_research_data_2.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>There are many shades of open access and they are all black</title><link href="http://tomp.io/new-colour-of-open-access-0A0A0A.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-12-06T14:20:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Tom Pollard</name></author><id>tag:tomp.io,2014-12-06:new-colour-of-open-access-0A0A0A.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;meta name="twitter:card" content="photo" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:site" content="@tompollard" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:title" content="There are many shades of open access and they are all black" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:description" content="#OAOAOA: the colour of open access" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:image" content="http://tomp.io/images/2014-12-06_0A0A0A.png" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:url" content="http://tomp.io/new-colour-of-open-access-0A0A0A" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The new colour of open access: #OAOAOA" src="images/2014-12-06_0A0A0A.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open access has been linked to various colours, most notably &lt;a href="http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/420454.article"&gt;green and gold&lt;/a&gt;. These colours are responsible for one of the most confusing thoughts I've come across in a long time: &lt;a href="http://openaccess.eprints.org/index.php?/archives/1062-Pre-Green-Fools-Gold-and-Post-Green-Fair-Gold-OA.html"&gt;pre-green fool's-gold and post-green fair-gold&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Green and gold terminology is not good: it reinforces belief that open access can only happen in two ways, which limits the way we think. Cameron Neylon pointed this out in the &lt;a href="http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/comment/opinion/lets-get-this-straight/2002789.article"&gt;Times Higher Education&lt;/a&gt; over a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we want to achieve open and collaborative research, we need to shed a lot of historical baggage. Not only nonsense colours, but journal impact factors as measures of quality, citations to paywalled articles when open versions exist, and the &lt;a href="http://www.aaas.org/"&gt;AAAS&lt;/a&gt;*.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then we need people to fill the voids. We need to work together to create a culture of open and collaborative research by changing mindsets and improving technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I'm going to stick with one colour for open access - #OAOAOA - and I'd love it if you would do the same.  &lt;!-- There are many shades of #OAOAOA and they are all black: --&gt; Does it need to be more complicated?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open access means unrestricted online access to peer-reviewed scholarly research&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="There are many shades of open access and they are all black" src="images/2014-12-06_shades_of_0A0A0A.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Only joking about the AAAS. Mostly. I am a little disappointed that they didn't have the courtesy to respond to &lt;a href="http://www.newstatesman.com/science/2014/08/new-scientific-journal-science-advance-condemned-open-access-advocates"&gt;this open letter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>More Cube Than Content</title><link href="http://tomp.io/nature-readcube-morecubethancontent.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-12-04T11:19:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Tom Pollard</name></author><id>tag:tomp.io,2014-12-04:nature-readcube-morecubethancontent.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;meta name="twitter:card" content="photo" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:site" content="@tompollard" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:title" content="More Cube Than Content" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:description" content="Nature have announced that they will allow people to share articles via ReadCube" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:image" content="http://tomp.io/images/2014-12-04_nature_readcube.png" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:url" content="http://tomp.io/nature-readcube-morecubethancontent" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nature have &lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/news/nature-makes-all-articles-free-to-view-1.16460"&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that they will be allowing people to share articles via links generated by a Macmillan-owned service called &lt;a href="http://readcube.com/"&gt;ReadCube&lt;/a&gt; in order to &lt;em&gt;support collaborative research&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Articles on nature.com to be made widely available to read and share to support collaborative research" src="images/2014-12-04_nature_readcube.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one way this is good: Nature are acknowledging that they have a problem with their publishing model (just like Science did when they &lt;a href="http://www.sciencemag.org/site/extra/ebola/"&gt;released Ebola content from behind their paywall&lt;/a&gt; in response to the ongoing epidemic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the announcement does nothing to solve the problem (in the same way that Science's response to the Ebola epidemic disregards the fact that the journal locks up plenty of research on other nasty diseases, as &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Stephen_Curry"&gt;Stephen Curry&lt;/a&gt; pointed out to me yesterday). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nature's system is unsatisfactory because it exerts proprietary control over publicly-funded content that has value in being shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last night, Noah Gray, a senior editor at Nature excitedly shared his first paper over Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--![A 3D head-direction mechanism in bats may support navigation in 3D space. My 1st shared @nature link for free reading.](images/2014-12-04_nature_readcube1.png)--&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A 3D head-direction mechanism in bats may support navigation in 3D space &lt;a href="http://t.co/EYg621Pnwx"&gt;http://t.co/EYg621Pnwx&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#10;My 1st shared &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nature"&gt;@nature&lt;/a&gt; link for free reading.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Noah Gray (@noahWG) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/noahWG/status/540258843448844288"&gt;December 3, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I clicked on the link using my laptop and waited for the article to appear, but the rotating ReadCube got &lt;em&gt;lots&lt;/em&gt; more airtime than the content (&lt;a href="http://vimeo.com/tompollard/naturereadcube"&gt;video here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--!![I get a nonstop spinning cube (mac, firefox). The article appears for an instant when I refresh, then disappears.](images/2014-12-04_nature_readcube2.png)--&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/readcube"&gt;@readcube&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/noahWG"&gt;@noahWG&lt;/a&gt; I get a nonstop spinning cube (mac, firefox). The article appears for an instant when I refresh, then disappears.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Tom Pollard (@tompollard) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/tompollard/status/540311489601896449"&gt;December 4, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/prerana123"&gt;Prerana Shrestha&lt;/a&gt;, meanwhile, couldn't read the article on her mobile device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--!![does the readcube link not work for mobile devices?](images/2014-12-04_nature_readcube3.png)--&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/noahWG"&gt;@noahWG&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nature"&gt;@nature&lt;/a&gt; does the readcube link not work for mobile devices?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Prerana Shrestha (@prerana123) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/prerana123/status/540261835220729856"&gt;December 3, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Nature's sharing system to succeed, we are entirely reliant on Readcube providing a robust service. ReadCube's failure to deliver on its promise, for whatever reason, means that Noah's gesture also failed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--!![Maybe that was just a reeeeaaally popular article &amp; you crashed the server.](images/2014-12-04_nature_readcube4.png)--&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/tompollard"&gt;@tompollard&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/readcube"&gt;@readcube&lt;/a&gt; works for me in Firefox on a PC. Maybe that was just a reeeeaaally popular article &amp;amp; you crashed the server.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Noah Gray (@noahWG) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/noahWG/status/540321000274264064"&gt;December 4, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I crashed the server or maybe this is a ham-fisted attempt to control publicly-funded research content. The result is the same: the value of the content is completely negated. Even if I'd been able to access the article, Nature prevents me from printing it or adding it to my reference manager. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This announcement isn't about supporting collaborative research, it's about controlling content through the ReadCube platform. If the content was open access, we could &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; help to deliver it to wherever it needs to be, whether that's a classroom, a clinic, or someone's phone. &lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Software Carpentry Instructor Training</title><link href="http://tomp.io/software-carpentry-instructor-training.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-10-27T12:33:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Tom Pollard</name></author><id>tag:tomp.io,2014-10-27:software-carpentry-instructor-training.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;meta name="twitter:card" content="photo" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:site" content="@tompollard" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:title" content="Software Carpentry Instructor Training" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:description" content="Software Carpentry equips researchers with skills for better programming" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:image" content="http://tomp.io/images/2014-10-27_greg_wilson.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:url" content="http://tomp.io/software-carpentry-instructor-training" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many researchers write and use software, but few receive formal training. Software Carpentry, largely run by volunteers, offers two day workshops around the world to equip researchers with core skills for better programming. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Software Carpentry Logo" src="images/2014-10-27_software_carpentry_logo.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three years ago I attended my first &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; workshop at &lt;a href="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/"&gt;UCL&lt;/a&gt;, where I learnt about scientific Python, test-driven development, and shell scripting. Last week I joined around 40 people at &lt;a href="http://www.tgac.ac.uk/"&gt;TGAC&lt;/a&gt; for a Software Carpentry Instructor course, led by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gvwilson"&gt;Greg Wilson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/billdoesphysics"&gt;Bill Mills&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/aleksandrana"&gt;Aleksandra Pawlik&lt;/a&gt;. I have cherry picked a few of my favourite bits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;"Motivation is the single biggest predictor of outcome"&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary predictor of a student's success is level of motivation. So for a teacher, creating enthusiasm (or not killing it) is as important as giving knowledge. Teaching should be treated as a performance, inspiring confidence and encouraging participation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Greg Wilson" src="images/2014-10-27_greg_wilson.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After sharing stories of the times that we had been demotivated as students, Greg noted that most of the negative experiences could be grouped into either feeling 1) ignored or 2) unfairly treated. So be inclusive and be fair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know your students&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tailor lessons to the distribution of prior knowledge in the class. Pre-course assessments can help to set the starting point, but care is needed to avoid scaring students away or capturing meaningless information (for example, watch out for the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect"&gt;Dunning-Kruger effect&lt;/a&gt;). The Software Carpentry pre-assessment for learners is &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org/workshops/assess/pre-learner.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Formative_assessment"&gt;Formative assessment&lt;/a&gt;' can be used to guide the learning process. One example is asking multiple choice questions during a lesson, where incorrect answers have diagnostic power (for example, see &lt;a href="http://teaching.software-carpentry.org/2013/02/06/2-4-multiple-choice-questions-unix-and-python/"&gt;this discussion&lt;/a&gt;). Ask students to vote for answers by holding up coloured paper. After the first round of voting, encourage pair discussion, followed by a second vote (there is a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2LbuoxAy56o"&gt;nice example here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adapt to the class, focusing on the areas that are most needed. This is the curse of the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massive_open_online_course"&gt;MOOC&lt;/a&gt;: students often don't complete online courses because they skip the bits that they know or don't need to know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create connections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good community-builder introduces people by highlighting their shared interests. A good teacher introduces new information by linking it to existing knowledge. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Draw a 'concept map', outlining the subject and describing how individual elements link together (see, for example, this map on &lt;a href="http://teaching.software-carpentry.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/03/20130326_Concept_map_Command_Line_Parameters_Steven_Koenig_revised.jpg"&gt;command line parameters&lt;/a&gt; and this one on &lt;a href="http://teaching.software-carpentry.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/Climbing_Anchor_Checks.jpg"&gt;stripping climbing gear&lt;/a&gt;). Use the map to guide the lesson plan, creating a path from current knowledge to the learning goal. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When teaching, avoid referring to new concepts before they have been taught ('forward referencing'). Apparently we can only hold &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Magical_Number_Seven,_Plus_or_Minus_Two"&gt;around seven&lt;/a&gt; temporary thoughts at a time, so don't waste head space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feedback is crucial&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the course we were frequently encouraged to give feedback, for example by handing in comments at the end of lessons (try Googling &lt;a href="https://www.google.co.uk/search?q=software+carpentry+feedback&amp;amp;ie=utf-8&amp;amp;oe=utf-8&amp;amp;aq=t&amp;amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;amp;client=firefox-a&amp;amp;channel=sb&amp;amp;gfe_rd=cr&amp;amp;ei=SzlOVJL1BdHH8geH4oGoBg#rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;amp;channel=sb&amp;amp;q=Software+Carpentry+feedback"&gt;"Software Carpentry feedback"&lt;/a&gt; and you'll see how seriously the team take this). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the activities that I found most useful, and most uncomfortable, was taking turns to teach and receive feedback. My first attempt is here (there was no planning time, so the content is just a stream of thoughts). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src="//player.vimeo.com/video/110147368" width="500" height="375" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://vimeo.com/110147368"&gt;Software Carpentry: First Feedback Session&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://vimeo.com/tompollard"&gt;tom pollard&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://vimeo.com"&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reviewing the video highlighted my defensive body position and 'constant' voice, so these were areas I worked on next time around!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the great things about encouraging feedback in class is that it not only helps you to improve, but it shows that you value the opinion of participants too. Win, win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Opposite of love is indifference" src="images/2014-10-27_opposite_of_love.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- 
&lt;video width="320" height="240" controls&gt;
&lt;source src="images/2014-10-27_firstone.mp4" type="video/mp4"&gt;
Your browser does not support the video tag.
&lt;/video&gt; --&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>How to access the MIMIC-II critical care database</title><link href="http://tomp.io/accessing-MIMIC-II.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-12T14:45:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Tom Pollard</name></author><id>tag:tomp.io,2014-09-12:accessing-MIMIC-II.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;meta name="twitter:card" content="photo" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:site" content="@tompollard" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:title" content="How to access the MIMIC-II critical care database" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:description" content="The MIMIC-II Critical Care Datathon" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:image" content="http://tomp.io/images/2014-09-12_datamarathon1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:url" content="http://tomp.io/accessing-MIMIC-II" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last weekend &lt;a href="http://criticaldata.mit.edu/datamarathon/organizers/"&gt;we&lt;/a&gt; hosted a &lt;a href="http://criticaldata.mit.edu/datamarathon/schedule/#london"&gt;Critical Data Marathon&lt;/a&gt; in London, alongside parallel events in France (Paris) and the US (Cambridge, MA). The idea was to bring together healthcare providers with data scientists to answer clinically-relevant questions over the course of a weekend. Many thanks to &lt;a href="http://mycommunity.theiet.org/communities/home/58"&gt;The Institution of Engineering and Technology&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.idea-london.co.uk/"&gt;IDEALondon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/"&gt;UCL&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/index.aspx"&gt;KCL&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www3.imperial.ac.uk/"&gt;Imperial College&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://criticaldata.mit.edu/datamarathon/organizers/"&gt;MIT&lt;/a&gt; for helping to make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Working together at the Critical Data Marathon" src="images/2014-09-12_datamarathon1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our focus was the &lt;a href="https://mimic.physionet.org/"&gt;MIMIC-II database&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="#Saeed"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, an incredible resource of critical care data. Aside from some minor hiccups along the way (like getting locked out of the venue on Sunday morning!) I think it's fair to say that the event was a success. We kicked off with some great talks, learnt about MIMIC-II, got to know each other, and even made a start on some clinical questions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As anticipated, one of the biggest challenges of the weekend was getting everyone set up with access to MIMIC-II. Not easy with around forty people, each with different skillsets, operating systems, and motivations. Data in MIMIC-II is anonymised but it relates to patients and requires respect, so there are a few hurdles that need to be jumped before access is granted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below I have documented what ended up being the most straightforward route to accessing the MIMIC-II data, in case it is helpful for others. If you're a clinical researcher fed up with battling your own hospital's data management systems, you could do worse than spending a few hours on the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Register with Physionet, the platform that hosts MIMIC-II (and a great source of data in itself). Simply add your details to the &lt;a href="https://physionet.org/pnw/login"&gt;Physionet registration page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete an approved online ethics training programme in human research, such as the NIH one on &lt;a href="https://phrp.nihtraining.com/users/login.php"&gt;Protecting Human Research Participants&lt;/a&gt;. This will take a couple of hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the &lt;a href="https://physionet.org/works/MIMICIIClinicalDatabase/access.shtml"&gt;MIMIC-II access instructions&lt;/a&gt; and, assuming you agree, click 'I agree' at the bottom of the page. You'll receive an email containing a 'Data Use Agreement'. Complete the agreement and send it to the email address provided, along with a copy of your ethics certificate. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After carrying out some checks, the MIMIC-II team will send you an email to let you know that permission to access the data has been granted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you've gained access there are several different methods for exploring and analysing the data. The most popular options amongst attendees of the London Data Marathon were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mimic.physionet.org/database/explorer/65-query-builder.html"&gt;MIMIC Explorer&lt;/a&gt;. This is a web-based tool that allows users to view tables and run queries. Exports are limited to 1000 rows, so while it's great for exploring the data, it's not so great for in-depth analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Working together at the Critical Data Marathon" src="images/2014-09-12_mimicexplorer.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Local Postgres instance. Setting up a local version of MIMIC-II is the simplest option for people who plan to use the data long-term. Install Postgres, import a dump of the data (you should be able to request this from the MIMIC-II team), and you're ready to go. We found that recreating the database takes around an hour on a solid state harddrive and requires about 60GB of space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://physionet.org/works/MIMICIIClinicalDatabase/files/"&gt;Flat text files&lt;/a&gt;. The entire clinical database is available as a collection of CSV files. Great for experienced programmers like &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/MattDowle"&gt;@MattDowle&lt;/a&gt;, who demonstrated the power of R at the data marathon!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all for now. Hopefully see you at the next MIMIC-II event, which is likely to be in mid-2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a name="Saeed"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Mohammed Saeed, MD, PhD, Mauricio Villarroel, MBA, Andrew T. Reisner, MD, Gari Clifford, PhD, Li-Wei Lehman, PhD, George Moody, Thomas Heldt, PhD, Tin H. Kyaw, Benjamin Moody, and Roger G. Mark, MD, PhD. &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3124312/"&gt;Multiparameter Intelligent Monitoring in Intensive Care II (MIMIC-II): A public-access intensive care unit database&lt;/a&gt; 2011; 39:952-960. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Writing your CV with Markdown and Pandoc</title><link href="http://tomp.io/markdown-cv.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-09-10T16:53:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Tom Pollard</name></author><id>tag:tomp.io,2014-09-10:markdown-cv.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;meta name="twitter:card" content="photo" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:site" content="@tompollard" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:title" content="Writing your CV with Markdown and Pandoc" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:description" content="A cleaner way to create your CV" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:image" content="http://tomp.io/images/2014-09-23_markdown_cv.png" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:url" content="http://tomp.io/markdown-cv" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few months ago &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/drstevok"&gt;Steve Harris&lt;/a&gt; introduced me to the pleasures of writing in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown"&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;. Since then it has been my format of choice for anything text-based. Simple, clear, and non-crashy. So much nicer than working with Word. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least one person thinks &lt;a href="http://labandfield.wordpress.com/2013/08/08/beware-the-academic-hipster-or-use-what-works-for-you/"&gt;Markdown is for hipsters&lt;/a&gt; but (a) I like hipsters and (b) maybe he's never experienced the horror of opening a Word file saved as HTML. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markdown is easily converted to all sorts of document types with &lt;a href="http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/"&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt;, making it a great native format. You write in Markdown and convert to DOC, PDF, etc when necessary. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of people write their CVs in Markdown already, but it took me a little time to find a style I liked for the PDF output. I ended up using a template by &lt;a href="http://craigeley.com/09-05-2013/formatting-your-cv-with-markdown-and-latex/"&gt;Craig Eley&lt;/a&gt;, with a couple of minor changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="CV created in Markdown" src="images/2014-09-23_markdown_cv.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modified version is online at: 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/tompollard/markdown-cv"&gt;https://github.com/tompollard/markdown-cv&lt;/a&gt;. To produce a PDF of your CV: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Edit the &lt;a href="https://github.com/tompollard/markdown-cv/tree/master/source"&gt;source/cv.md&lt;/a&gt; file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run 'make pdf' in &lt;a href="https://github.com/tompollard/markdown-cv"&gt;the folder&lt;/a&gt; containing the Makefile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pick up the PDF from &lt;a href="https://github.com/tompollard/markdown-cv/tree/master/output"&gt;output/cv.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://latex-project.org/ftp.html"&gt;Latex&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://johnmacfarlane.net/pandoc/"&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt; will need to be installed on your system for this to work. You can modify and improve the style by editing the template at &lt;a href="https://github.com/tompollard/markdown-cv/tree/master/source/style"&gt;source/style/template.tex&lt;/a&gt; (Pandoc creates PDFs via Latex).&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Why you shouldn't refuse to review articles for Elsevier</title><link href="http://tomp.io/refuse-to-review.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-08-14T17:19:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Tom Pollard</name></author><id>tag:tomp.io,2014-08-14:refuse-to-review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;meta name="twitter:card" content="photo" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:site" content="@tompollard" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:title" content="Why you shouldn't refuse to review articles for Elsevier" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:description" content="Won't publish, won't referee, won't do editorial work..." /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:image" content="http://tomp.io/images/2014-08-14_boycott_journals.png" /&gt;
&lt;meta name="twitter:url" content="http://tomp.io/refuse-to-review" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fair number of people refuse to review for certain journals, based on their &lt;a href="http://thecostofknowledge.com/"&gt;pro&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://www.loria.fr/~zimmerma/open_access.html"&gt;anti&lt;/a&gt; open-access stance. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Won't publish, won't referee, won't do editorial work" src="images/2014-08-14_boycott_journals.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href="http://www.elsevier.com/reviewers/frequently-asked-questions#are-there-consequences-for-refusing-to-review-a-paper"&gt;Elsevier tells us&lt;/a&gt;, that's fine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Are there any consequences of refusing to review?" src="images/2014-08-14_refuse_to_review.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refusal gets the message to the editors, but the authors are the people that prop up the journal (assuming reviewers will always be found somewhere). So it seems better to accept the invitation to review and to include a comment to the authors along the lines of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We note that the authors have chosen to submit their article to {JOURNALTITLE}. Have the authors considered alternatives, such as {JOURNALTITLE} and {JOURNALTITLE}? These journals are preferable because ... &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the very least it'll keep the editors on their toes. If the message reaches the authors, it could be powerful. Targeted, from a place of authority, and hitting a captive audience. You might raise a few hackles, but that's why reviewers get anonymity ;)&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Hosting a Pelican blog on Github (1st post)</title><link href="http://tomp.io/pelican-github-blog.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-07T14:01:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Tom Pollard</name></author><id>tag:tomp.io,2014-07-07:pelican-github-blog.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This blog was created with the help of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://gandi.net/"&gt;Gandi&lt;/a&gt;, to register the domain name. Gandi in my experience are excellent. Zero spam, no upselling of unnecessary packages, and great community support. Plus, as far as I know, the staff &lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/03/31/bob-parsons-godaddy-ceo-elephant-hunt_n_843121.html"&gt;aren't elephant hunters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;, a simple python framework for creating static websites. Lacks the pizzazz of frameworks like Django, but that's okay (/good).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican-themes/tree/master/monospace"&gt;Monospace theme&lt;/a&gt; for Pelican. Might change later, but I like the simple look for now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;, for hosting the site. Offers free hosting for a single website, which is nice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://disqus.com/"&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt;, to allow comments. Initially I'd wanted to avoid relying on an external service for comments, but the simplicity of Disqus was difficult to argue with. They have nice customer service too, as it turns out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rough process was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;personal site&lt;/a&gt; on Github.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Register a domain with Gandi. &lt;a href="http://wiki.gandi.net/dokuwiki/en/dns/zone/a-record"&gt;Point domain&lt;/a&gt; to Github via the zone file. The settings will take a few hours to propogate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/"&gt;Clone Pelican&lt;/a&gt; into a local folder, on a branch named 'source'&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the theme files to the source branch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add personal settings to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/tompollard/tompollard.github.io/blob/source/pelicanconf.py"&gt;pelicanconf.py&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/tompollard/tompollard.github.io/blob/source/publishconf.py"&gt;publishconf.py&lt;/a&gt; files. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a favicon.ico and CNAME file to the source folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modify the 'github' command in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/tompollard/tompollard.github.io/blob/source/Makefile"&gt;Makefile&lt;/a&gt; to push to a personal site, rather than project site. Also add line to the 'publish' command to copy the favicon and CNAME files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add blog posts to the content folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run 'make github', which compiles the site on the 'master' branch and pushes to Github.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For an overview of the file structure, see the &lt;a href="https://github.com/tompollard/tompollard.github.io/tree/source"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/tompollard/tompollard.github.io"&gt;master&lt;/a&gt; branches on Github.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now, to add a new blog post, I create a markdown file to the content folder (on the source branch) and run 'make github'. Easy!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>